Kenneth Reforma

Data Analyst and Data Engineer

Mobile (+1) 437 265-0719 Email kenneth.reforma@gmail.com Location Mississauga, Ontario **LinkedIn** linkedin.com/in/kenneth-reforma **Github** github.com/kpreforma

Professional Summary

Experienced data analyst with 6 years of data analysis experience in energy markets, trading, and financial indices. Demonstratable skills include data modelling, forecasting, data warehousing, and process automation.

Skills

Data: data analysis, data engineering, data cleansing, data warehousing, ETL, ELT, Excel, MS Access, SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server, SQLite, MongoDB, Google Sheets, time-series

Excel: index-match, vlookup, macro/VBA, power query, conditional formatting, pivot tables, filters

Cloud: Microsoft Azure, virtual machine, load balancing, AWS Workspaces S3-EC2-RDS

Development: VBA, Python (selenium, pandas, pyspark, plotly, dash), Jupyter, Spark, Airflow, Docker, Postgres, SQL Server, Oracle, PL/SQL, Java, C, C++, Git, GitHub, Javascript, Talend **Analytics:** PowerBI, Tableau, TIBCO Spotfire

Warehousing: Snowflake, Google Big Query, Oracle, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQL Server, and MongoDB.

Experience

IT Analyst and Lab Assistant (Aug 2022 – present) part-time

Seneca College

- First response for IT concerns and troubleshooting equipment and computers hybrid learning.
- Logs and maintains troubleshooting techniques within the team using Google Sheets for information dissemination.
- Handles students' concerns regarding C/C++ programming by explaining concepts and making sure that workshop criteria are met.

Senior Industry Analyst (May 2017 – Jun 2022)

First Gen Corporation

- Implemented real-time data analysis to optimize revenues in the electricity market, ancillary services, and bilateral contracts through Excel models for profit maximization, competitor analysis, and cost minimization techniques.
- Created and maintained daily, weekly, and monthly trading and sales reports for reporting with management and chief executives.
- Developed real-time and batch-processed data visualizations for monitoring business operations, revenue, and forecast accuracy.
- Created ETL data pipelines/DAGs using Talend and Python to process business users from different sources to provide data for forecasting and trading operations.
- Authored complex Excel models to implement market strategies and enable efficient business processes with heavy use of index-match and VBA.
- Created SQL scripts used by the company for data extraction from internal data warehouse system into reports and visualization.

Kenneth Reforma

Data Analyst and Data Engineer

Mobile (+1) 437 265-0719 **Email** kenneth.reforma@gmail.com **Location** Mississauga, Ontario **LinkedIn** linkedin.com/in/kenneth-reforma **Github** github.com/kpreforma

- Created an end-to-end data processing and automation Python solution that helped the company save **CAD 10,000 monthly** in operational (manpower and overtime) cost.
- Created a bilateral contract declaration model in Excel to optimally distribute the company's
 generating capacity to 200 customers resulting in more than CAD 25,000 in revenue per
 month, improved customer satisfaction, and increased customer retention.
- Created, maintained, and streamlined trading and sales business processes by introducing automation and efficient data storage using PowerShell, VB for Applications, and SQL to support analytical tasks.
- Connected marketing Salesforce CRM system with Excel and Google Sheets with APIs.
- Coordinated with InfoSec Group to handle customer data privacy checkpoints for the CRM project and Data Warehouse system.
- Acted as the main point person between third-party IT vendors and business group for the business IT requirements.

Science Research Specialist (Jan 2016 - Apr 2017)

Department of Energy

- Developed and launched an in-house data warehouse system running on MySQL and PHP for policy formulation support.
- Created a database and extraction system for electricity market data that uses SQL to streamline data requests by other departments.
- Extracted thousands of unstructured raw data points every hour from the electricity market operator to use in management reports built in Excel.

Education

Graduated 2023 Computer Programming Diploma (GPA: 4.0)

Seneca College

Graduated 2014 Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering

University of the Philippines

Certifications

•	Microsoft 365 Certified: Fundamentals Microsoft	Jul 2023
•	Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Fundamentals Microsoft	Jul 2023
•	Retrieving, Processing, and Visualizing Data with Python Specialization University of Michigan (Coursera)	Nov 2020